{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Supporters of this legislation organized the “Prison Special” in which members of the Silent Sentinels traveled from city to city giving speeches. In a speech supporting this legislation, Woodrow Wilson asked if a certain group should only have “suffering and sacrifice” without “privilege and right.” Carrie Chapman Catt and Alice Paul rallied the NAWSA in support of this amendment. For ten points, name this amendment that gave women the right to vote.",
      "answer": "19th Amendment"
    },
    {
      "question": "A president of this country tried to avoid the ramifications of the Rywingate corruption scandal by claiming parliamentary commissions couldn’t investigate him. The President of the European Council, Donald Tusk, was Prime Minister of this country during the early 2010s. A trade union founded in this country’s Lenin Shipyards in 1980 was led by electrician and future President Lech Walesa [lek vah-WEN-sah]. For ten points, name this eastern European country where Solidarity rose to power in Warsaw.",
      "answer": "Poland"
    },
    {
      "question": "A character in this novel declares a wish to become a vivandi`ere in the Union Army to join her father, Robert, before he is wounded in 1862. John Brooke is also wounded in the Civil War and, with one of this novel’s title characters, becomes the father of twins Daisy and Demi. Professor Bhaer and Laurie Laurence marry two of the other March sisters in, for ten points, what novel by Louisa May Alcott about Meg, Jo, Beth, and Amy?",
      "answer": "Little Women"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city established a foothold in the Middle East after signing the Pactum Warmundi with Jerusalem. Julius II formed the League of Cambrai to combat the influence of this city. This city secured its influence in the Mediterranean following the War of Chioggia. This city was governed by a Council of Ten led by a Doge. For ten points, name this rival of Genoa, an Italian city-state known for its canals.",
      "answer": "Venice"
    },
    {
      "question": "A territory governed by this country contains the island of Saipan and is governed from the town of Capitol Hill. UN Security Council Resolution 21 gave this country the Northern Mariana Islands. During the Spanish Flu epidemic, John Martin Poyer quarantined an island territory of this country and its bay at Pago Pago. A portion of Samoa is governed by, for ten points, what country whose Pacific holdings also include Guam and Hawaii?",
      "answer": [
        "United States of America or America",
        "USA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this man’s presidency, the Insanity Defense Reform Act shifted the burden of proof for insanity defenses from the prosecution to the defense. This man’s press secretary, James Brady, received wounds that contributed to his death 33 years later when, due to his fixation on Jodie Foster, John Hinckley Jr. fired six shots at this man. For ten points, name this Republican President who was the target of an assassination attempt in 1981.",
      "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jamala won this event in 2016 by protesting the treatment of the Crimean Tatars in 1944. This event’s scoring reform in 2016 allowed participating countries to score twice as many “douze points” [dooz pwant] as before. This event was created in 1956 as an effort to popularize live TV throughout Western Europe. Australia is a guest competitor in, for ten points, what annual international song competition that was won in 2019 by the Netherlands?",
      "answer": "Eurovision Song Contest"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, a 90-day state of emergency edict was continually renewed by Alfred Stroessner for over 30 years. This country’s leader, Francisco Solano Lopez, died at the Battle of Cerro Cor´a near the end of the War of the Triple Alliance. This country defended the nearby Republic of Uruguay after it was invaded by Pedro II. For ten points, name this country where Brazilian forces occupied Asuncion´ at the end of a 1864 war.",
      "answer": "Paraguay"
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman was abducted after being tricked into boarding Samuel Argall’s ship. Alexander Whitaker converted this woman to Christianity and oversaw her baptism, upon which she took the name Rebecca. With Tomocomo, this woman traveled to England with her husband John Rolfe. This daughter of Powhatan legendarily stopped the execution of an English colonist by placing her head over his body. For ten points, name this Native American woman who may have saved John Smith.",
      "answer": [
        "Pocahontas",
        "Rebecca Rolfe before “Rolfe” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler was served by “spymaster” Francis Walsingham, who was succeeded by Robert Cecil. Following the Battle of Gravelines, this ruler addressed troops at Tilbury, claiming she had the “heart and stomach of a king.” This queen reinstated the Act of Supremacy which had been repealed as part of the Catholic reforms of Mary I. For ten points, name this “Virgin Queen,” the last Tudor monarch of England.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth I"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An ominous message reading this man “will die and his land will be divided” was written on a fallen meteor in Dongjun. Gao Jianli attempted to assassinate this man with a lute. This man, aided by Li Si, unified his country’s writing system. During this man’s rule, he carried out the “burning of the books and burying of the scholars” to promote legalism. The Warring States period was ended by, for ten points, what first Emperor of China?",
        "answer": [
          "Qin Shi Huangdi",
          "Zhao Zheng",
          "Ying Zheng"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Qin Shi Haungdi legendarily died after consuming pills of this substance trying to achieve immortality. A river of this substance was built for his tomb.",
        "answer": "mercury"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1793, the nascent United States government was forced to flee this city due to a yellow fever outbreak. William Howe captured this city after defeating forces under George Washington at the Battle of Brandywine. A landmark in this city was originally repaired by John Pass and John Stow after it cracked on its first use. The Liberty Bell is located in, for ten points, what city where the Declaration of Independence was signed, the largest city in Pennsylvania?",
        "answer": "Philadelphia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Philadelphia temporarily lost its status as capital of the United States after Congress was forced to flee to this city during a 1783 revolt.",
        "answer": "New York City"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Thisscientistnamesalawthatrelatestheproductoftwomasseswiththeinversesquareofthedistance separating them. This thinker’s essay General Scholium, which included the quotation “Hypotheses non fingo,” was an addendum to his Principia. Independent of Gottfried Leibniz, this scientist invented calculus. For ten points, name this scientist whose laws of inertia, acceleration, and action and reaction form the three laws of motion.",
        "answer": "Sir Isaac Newton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Isaac Newton’s work on the three laws of motion developed from this earlier scientist’s three laws of planetary motion.",
        "answer": "Johannes Kepler"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Claudius Gothicus died during one of these events named for Cyprian. A diplomatic mission to China may have caused one of these events that likely claimed the life of Lucius Verus. Over 5 million people may have died in an event of this type that began under, and is named for, Antoninus Pius. Galen observed that fevers and boils were common symptoms of one of these events. For ten points, name these events, massive outbreaks of disease.",
        "answer": "plagues"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 541 AD plague occurred during the reign of this Byzantine Emperor, causing the reversal of Belisarius” conquests.",
        "answer": [
          "Justinian I",
          "Justinian the Great"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The settlement house movement sought to help people facing this condition by introducing them to middle class values. In Nickel and Dimed, Barbara Ehrenreich examined this condition among employed people. This condition is defined as having an income less than three times the average food budget in the United States, while the extreme form of this condition is often identified as living on less than a dollar a day. For ten points, name this condition characterized by a lack of money.",
        "answer": [
          "poverty",
          "obvious equivalents such as being poor",
          "material hardship"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ehrenreich’s Nickel and Dimed includes a section on this corporation, the subject of a 2005 documentary subtitled The High Cost of Low Price. This company’s founder, Sam Walton, was the richest man in America for much of the 1980s.",
        "answer": "Wal-Mart Inc."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Wilhelm Furtwangler conducted this piece at the 1951 re-opening of the Bayreuth [bye-ROYT] Festival. The piece’s finale features a 6/8 Turkish March and includes a bass soloist who sings “O friends, not these tones!” Leonard Bernstein substituted the word “Freiheit” [FRY-hite] for “Freude” [froy-deh] when conducting this piece after the fall of the Berlin Wall. Friedrich Schiller’s poem “Ode to Joy” is set to music in, for ten points, what symphony, the last by Ludwig van Beethoven?",
        "answer": [
          "Symphony No. 9 in D minor by Ludwig van Beethoven [",
          "9 alone after “Beethoven” is read",
          "Choral Symphony"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This composer orchestrated an arrangement of Beethoven’s 9th Symphony for the 1872 opening of the Bayreuth Festival Theater, where this man premiered his Ring cycle four years later.",
        "answer": "Richard Wagner"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the coronation of this man, several people were trampled to death as a crowd rushed to Khodynka field. On the advice of Sergei Witte, this man curbed his own power in the October Manifesto to appease the people. This man and his immediate family were executed in Yekaterinburg to prevent them from being rescued by the White Army. The 1917 October Revolution caused the resignation of, for ten points, what final Romanov ruler, the last Tsar of Russia?",
        "answer": "Nicholas II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nicholas II’s wife was obsessed with this Russian mystic who claimed he could heal their son of his hemophilia.",
        "answer": "Grigori Rasputin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A member of this family who married Sargent Shriver was inspired by her intellectually disabled sister to found the Special Olympics. A politician from this family drove his car off a bridge, killing Mary Jo Kopechne [koe-PECK-nee], in the Chappaquiddick Incident. Sirhan Sirhan assassinated a member of this family who had earlier served as his brother’s Attorney General. For ten points, name this family which included President John Fitzgerald.",
        "answer": "Kennedy family"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Kennedy Dynasty was based in this state where the Kennedy Compound is located in Hyannis Port.",
        "answer": "Massachusetts"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Abraham Lincoln",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State he served as a Representative until 1849.",
          "answer": "Illinois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party, founded to oppose slavery, that nominated him for President in 1860.",
          "answer": [
            "Republican Party",
            "Grand Old Party",
            "GOP"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular actor who assassinated him in Ford’s Theater.",
          "answer": "John Wilkes Booth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman who married him in 1842 and entered a deep depression after his death.",
          "answer": [
            "Mary Todd Lincoln",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Right against unlawful imprisonment that Lincoln suspended during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Habeas corpus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Union general who ran against him in the Election of 1864.",
          "answer": "George B. McClellan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician he opposed for a Senate seat in 1858; they engaged in a series of crucial debates.",
          "answer": "Stephen Douglas"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where that opponent outlined a namesake doctrine supporting popular sovereignty in a debate with Lincoln.",
          "answer": "Freeport Doctrine"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Early Democracy in Britain",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1215 document that formed the basis of British democracy.",
          "answer": [
            "Magna Carta Libertatum",
            "Great Charter of the Liberties"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Town outside Windsor where that document was signed.",
          "answer": "Runnymede"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legislative body, containing the House of Lords, that gained new powers after 1215.",
          "answer": "Parliament"
        },
        {
          "question": "English King who was forced to give up some of his power in 1215.",
          "answer": [
            "King John I",
            "John Lackland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Noble rank held by Robert Fitzwalter and the other men rebelling against that king’s rule.",
          "answer": "baron"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where a set of 1258 “Provisions” created more representation, and where the oldest English- speaking university is found.",
          "answer": "Provisions of Oxford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who annulled the 1215 document.",
          "answer": "Innocent III"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who, in exchange for a tax, reconfirmed that 1215 document.",
          "answer": [
            "Edward I of England",
            "Edward Longshanks"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Explorers",
      "prompt": "Name the explorer who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "led an expedition to the new world on the Santa Maria.",
          "answer": "Christopher Columbus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave a detailed account of China in his Travels.",
          "answer": "Marco Polo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed in Hawaii while attempting to kidnap Kalani’opu’u.",
          "answer": "James Cook"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first European to discover Brazil.",
          "answer": "Pedro Cabral"
        },
        {
          "question": "Discovered a direct sea route to India, starting in 1497, for Portugal.",
          "answer": "Vasco da Gama"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sailed the coast of North America in 1497 for Henry VII.",
          "answer": "John Cabot or Giovanni Caboto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first to sail around the southernmost tip of Africa.",
          "answer": "Bartolomeu Dias"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explored New York Bay and is the namesake of a bridge that crosses the Narrows.",
          "answer": "Giovanni da Verrazzano"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Daniel F. O’Leary refused to obey this man’s orders to burn his personal letters after his death. Manuela Saenz protected this man from an assassination attempt after winning the Battle of Pichincha. The (20 pts)",
        "Decree of War to the Death was passed by this man to punish those who helped enemy forces during his (10 pts)",
        "Admirable Campaign. The first President of Gran Colombia was, for ten points, what “liberator” of South America who is honored as the namesake of a country with capitals Sucre and La Paz?"
      ],
      "answer": "Simon Bolivar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler ordered Gnaeus Corbulo to invade Armenia, which nearly sparked a war with Vologases I’s Parthian Empire. Suetonius suppressed (20 pts)",
        "Boudicca’s revolt during the reign of this man. The Domus Aurea was commissioned by this man, who may have orchestrated a (10 pts)",
        "disaster in his capital to make room for it. The Year of the Four Emperors began after the assassination of this man, whose popularity plummeted due to a 64 AD fire. For ten points, name this emperor accused of fiddling while Rome burned."
      ],
      "answer": "Nero Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one story, Vishnu warns Manu of one of these events known as the pralaya, a word that translates to “dissolution.” In the Epic of Gilgamesh, Utnapishtim and his wife are the (20 pts)",
        "sole survivors of one of these disasters. A man survives another one of these events with his sons Shem, Ham and Japheth, eventually (10 pts)",
        "landing on Mount Ararat. Historical theories have been developed to explain why various cultures have a myth about, for ten points, what type of disaster that, in the Book of Genesis, wipes out most of humanity, except those aboard Noah’s ark?"
      ],
      "answer": "mythical floods or deluges"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist, who painted a yellow bedframe in his blue Bedroom at Arles, failed to sell most of his still-lives of roses, irises and sunflowers during his lifetime. Self-portraits with a straw hat and (20 pts)",
        "bandage were painted by this man, whose most famous work was created while institutionalized in Saint-R´emy. Cypress (10 pts)",
        "trees rise up into a swirled blue and yellow evening sky in a work by, for ten points, what Dutch artist of The Starry Night who famously cut off his own ear?"
      ],
      "answer": "Vincent Willem van Gogh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the aftermath of this battle, captured soldiers formed the Convention Army. Timothy Murphy may have killed Simon (20 pts)",
        "Fraser at this battle on the orders of Daniel Morgan. The American victory at this battle ended a campaign to secure the (10 pts)",
        "Hudson River Valley led by John Burgoyne. Horatio Gates and Benedict Arnold led American troops in, for ten points, what decisive 1777 battle that convinced the French to join the Revolutionary War?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Saratoga",
        "Battle of Freeman’s Farm",
        "Battle of Bemis Heights"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This modern-day country was home to a group of European social elites called the Happy Valley Set; that group included many farm owners in its White Highlands and its last governor, Evelyn Baring. (20 pts)",
        "Dedan Kimathi led a rebellion in this country that grew out of a movement of oathing ceremonies among its Kikuyu people. The (10 pts)",
        "Mau Mau Rebellion challenged British rule of, for ten points, what East African country with capital Nairobi?"
      ],
      "answer": "Kenya"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A leader of this city, Cleombrotus I, was killed at the 371 BC Battle of Leuctra. A fleet from this city, under the command of (20 pts)",
        "Lysander, won the Battle of Aegospotami near the end of the Peloponnesian War. In this city, Cinadon attempted to overthrow the (10 pts)",
        "Eurypontid King Agesilaus II with the help of the helots. Three hundred soldiers from this city fought a valiant battle against invading Persian forces at the Battle of Thermopylae. Leonidas led, for ten points, what Greek city-state, the arch-rival to Athens?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sparta"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A company in this industry was supported by the Robert McNamara-led Whiz Kids. After the passing of the (20 pts)",
        "Wagner Act, 130,000 workers in this industry participated in a forty-four day sit-in in Flint, (10 pts)",
        "Michigan. With the help of the IWW, the first strike in this industry halted production of the Studebaker plant. The UAW is a union in, for ten points, what industry in which workers are employed by Ford and GM?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Automobile industry",
        "answers related to cars"
      ]
    }
  ]
}